<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../xslt2html_6014_resources.xsl"?>

<resources>

the boy who was raised as a dog
Bruce D. Perry
618.92 Perry
Focused on how trauma effects children, this covers many stories in detail from which people have faced during their younger years. Covers topics interpretively such as the neuroscience and developmental theory behind how trauma effects a person, especially those who are children. This is written narratively, and covers many forms of trauma, but brings home a clear message about resilience and recovering from trauma.
neglect, abuse, very popular, survival, neuroscience


Basic concepts of psychiatric-mental health nursing
Author: Shives, Louise Rebraca.
610.7368 Shives
Covers topics essential for nurses to know about working with trauma victims and covers skills necessary for providing care to these patients. Additionally covers specific clinical facts, such as diagnostic criteria in the DSM-IV-TR and psycho-pharmacological information, amongst other resources.
medical, psychological, nursing, trauma

Mosby's pediatric nursing reference
Author: Betz, Cecily Lynn.
610.73 Mosby's DAVIE
Contains appendices on mental health, non-accidental trauma, and growth charts that is essential to those working with children.
medical, psychological, nursing

Guiding children's social development : theory to practice
by  Kostelnik, Marjorie J.
155.4 Gui
Developed to guide working with children in a classroom, it covers topics such as improving self esteem and interpreting student behavior.
education, developmental stages, psychological

The first three years & beyond : brain development and social policy
by  Zigler, Edward, 1930-
305.231 Zig DAVIE
Written targeting parents and policymakers, this gives a background on how childrens' brains develop and addressing problems that occur during early childhood development. The key chapter for this is chapter 6, which covers Child Abuse and the Brain
developmental stages, education, abuse

Toxic parents : overcoming their hurtful legacy and reclaiming your life
Author: Forward, Susan.
362.829 Forward DAVIE
For those that have struggled through childhood with maltreatment, this gives context to how the trauma is not the child's fault. For those in education, medical fields, or generally researching about trauma, this can give context to what abuse and neglect does, and signs to listen for people casually mentioning that indicate that home was not or is not safe.
abuse, neglect, trauma, psychological, survival

Raising Cain : protecting the emotional life of boys
by  Kindlon, Daniel J. (Daniel James), 1953-
1999, Davidson |   305.23 Kindlon
2000, Davie |  305.23 Kindlon DAVIE
The context that boys grow up in commonly forces them to reject their own emotions and not develop emotional literacy. For those who work with boys, this supplements knowledge about improving children's emotional literacy and addressing this at school and home.
trauma, psychological, developmental stages

The lost boy : a foster child's search for the love of a family
by  Pelzer, David J.
362 Pelzer
This comes from a primary source discussing the effects of losing the birth family as a foster child. It covers topics such as the assumption by many that foster children are too troublesome and some that care for them feel resentment towards the children simply because they are a foster child.
neglect, abuse, trauma, psychological


Your body belongs to you
Author: Spelman, Cornelia, author.
J 613.6 Spe
This covers education on sexual abuse and informing children that they are allowed to say no to being touched.
abuse, trauma, education, very popular

The scared child : helping kids overcome traumatic events
by  Brooks, Barbara, 1937-
155.93 Bro DAVIE
Working with kids, be it as a parent, teacher, social worker, or other position that is in contact with children often, this covers tactics for encouraging children to express their fear in a way that helps them cope.
abuse, neglect, trauma, psychological, developmental stages

A child called "it" : one child's courage to survive
by  Pelzer, David J., author.
362.7 Pel DAVIE
Covers an extreme case of child abuse, discussing the events of what happened clearly. Using this as a resource for having clear trauma experiences to refer to can solidify understanding of other materials discussing working with others who have experienced forms of trauma such as abuse and neglect. Despite it being extreme, it also can give context to individual events that may lead to developmental trauma.
neglect, abuse, trauma, psychological, survival, very popular

The Color Purple
by  Walker, Alice, 1944-
F Wal
Even though this is fiction, it provides insight into how sexual abuse effects those who experience it, especially the sense of isolation. When working with those who have been abused, this is a viewport into how abuse changes a person's abilities to speak for themselves through the training by those who abused them into believing no one will help.
abuse, trauma, psychological, survival, very popular

</resources>
